How is it possible? They don't know anything." My colleagues said, "No, it's a simple solution. One of your students must have been passing by, showed them how to use the mouse." So I said, "Yeah, that's possible." So I repeated the experiment. I went 300 miles out of Delhi into a really remote village where the chances of a passing software development engineer was very little. (Laughter) I repeated the experiment there. There was no place to stay, so I stuck my computer in, I went away, came back after a couple of months, found kids playing games on it. When they saw me, they said, "We want a faster processor and a better mouse." (Laughter) So I said, "How on Earth do you know all this?" And they said something very interesting to me. In an irritated voice, they said, "You've given us a machine that works only in English, so we had to teach ourselves English in order to use it." (Laughter) That's the first time, as a teacher, that I had heard the word "teach ourselves" said so casually. Here's a short glimpse from those years. That's the first day at the Hole in the Wall. On your right is an eight-year-old. To his left is his student. She's six. And he's teaching her how to browse. Then onto other parts of the country, I repeated this over and over again, getting exactly the same results that we were. ["Hole in the wall film - 1999"] An eight-year-old telling his elder sister what to do. And finally a girl explaining in Marathi what it is, and said, "There's a processor inside." So I started publishing. I published everywhere. I wrote down and measured everything, and I said, in nine months, a group of children left alone with a computer in any language will reach the same standard as an office secretary in the West. I'd seen it happen over and over and over again. But I was curious to know, what else would they do if they could do this much? I started experimenting with other subjects, among them, for example, pronunciation. There's one community of children in southern India whose English pronunciation is really bad, and they needed good pronunciation because that would improve their jobs. I gave them a speech-to-text engine in a computer, and I said, "Keep talking into it until it types what you say." (Laughter) They did that, and watch a little bit of this. Computer: Nice to meet you.Child: Nice to meet you. Sugata Mitra: The reason I ended with the face of this young lady over there is because I suspect many of you know her. She has now joined a call center in Hyderabad and may have tortured you about your credit card bills in a very clear English accent. So then people said, well, how far will it go? Where does it stop? I decided I would destroy my own argument by creating an absurd proposition. I made a hypothesis, a ridiculous hypothesis. Tamil is a south Indian language, and I said, can Tamil-speaking children in a south Indian village learn the biotechnology of DNA replication in English from a streetside computer? And I said, I'll measure them. They'll get a zero. I'll spend a couple of months, I'll leave it for a couple of months, I'll go back, they'll get another zero. I'll go back to the lab and say, we need teachers. I found a village. It was called Kallikuppam in southern India. I put in Hole in the Wall computers there, downloaded all kinds of stuff from the Internet about DNA replication, most of which I didn't understand. The children came rushing, said, "What's all this?" So I said, "It's very topical, very important. But it's all in English." So they said, "How can we understand such big English words and diagrams and chemistry?" So by now, I had developed a new pedagogical method, so I applied that. I said, "I haven't the foggiest idea." (Laughter) "And anyway, I am going away." So I left them for a couple of months. They'd got a zero. I gave them a test. I came back after two months and the children trooped in and said, "We've understood nothing." So I said, "Well, what did I expect?" So I said, "Okay, but how long did it take you before you decided that you can't understand anything?" So they said, "We haven't given up. We look at it every single day." So I said, "What? You don't understand these screens and you keep staring at it for two months? What for?" So a little girl who you see just now, she raised her hand, and she says to me in broken Tamil and English, she said, "Well, apart from the fact that improper replication of the DNA molecule causes disease, we haven't understood anything else." (Laughter) (Applause) So I tested them. I got an educational impossibility, zero to 30 percent in two months in the tropical heat with a computer under the tree in a language they didn't know doing something that's a decade ahead of their time. Absurd. But I had to follow the Victorian norm. Thirty percent is a fail. How do I get them to pass? I have to get them 20 more marks. I couldn't find a teacher. What I did find was a friend that they had, a 22-year-old girl who was an accountant and she played with them all the time. So I asked this girl, "Can you help them?" So she says, "Absolutely not. I didn't have science in school. I have no idea what they're doing under that tree all day long. I can't help you." I said, "I'll tell you what. Use the method of the grandmother." So she says, "What's that?" I said, "Stand behind them. Whenever they do anything, you just say, 'Well, wow, I mean, how did you do that? What's the next page? Gosh, when I was your age, I could have never done that.' You know what grannies do." So she did that for two more months. The scores jumped to 50 percent. Kallikuppam had caught up with my control school in New Delhi, a rich private school with a trained biotechnology teacher. When I saw that graph I knew there is a way to level the playing field. Here's Kallikuppam. (Children speaking) Neurons ... communication. I got the camera angle wrong. That one is just amateur stuff, but what she was saying, as you could make out, was about neurons, with her hands were like that, and she was saying neurons communicate. At 12. So what are jobs going to be like? Well, we know what they're like today. What's learning going to be like? We know what it's like today, children pouring over with their mobile phones on the one hand and then reluctantly going to school to pick up their books with their other hand. What will it be tomorrow? Could it be that we don't need to go to school at all? Could it be that, at the point in time when you need to know something, you can find out in two minutes? Could it be -- a devastating question, a question that was framed for me by Nicholas Negroponte -- could it be that we are heading towards or maybe in a future where knowing is obsolete? But that's terrible. We are homo sapiens. Knowing, that's what distinguishes us from the apes. But look at it this way. It took nature 100 million years to make the ape stand up and become Homo sapiens. It took us only 10,000 to make knowing obsolete. What an achievement that is. But we have to integrate that into our own future. Encouragement seems to be the key. If you look at Kuppam, if you look at all of the experiments that I did, it was simply saying, "Wow," saluting learning. There is evidence from neuroscience. The reptilian part of our brain, which sits in the center of our brain, when it's threatened, it shuts down everything else, it shuts down the prefrontal cortex, the parts which learn, it shuts all of that down. Punishment and examinations are seen as threats. We take our children, we make them shut their brains down, and then we say, "Perform." Why did they create a system like that? Because it was needed. There was an age in the Age of Empires when you needed those people who can survive under threat. When you're standing in a trench all alone, if you could have survived, you're okay, you've passed. If you didn't, you failed. But the Age of Empires is gone. What happens to creativity in our age? We need to shift that balance back from threat to pleasure. I came back to England looking for British grandmothers. I put out notices in papers saying, if you are a British grandmother, if you have broadband and a web camera, can you give me one hour of your time per week for free? I got 200 in the first two weeks. I know more British grandmothers than anyone in the universe. (Laughter) They're called the Granny Cloud. The Granny Cloud sits on the Internet. If there's a child in trouble, we beam a Gran. She goes on over Skype and she sorts things out. I've seen them do it from a village called Diggles in northwestern England, deep inside a village in Tamil Nadu, India, 6,000 miles away. She does it with only one age-old gesture. "Shhh." Okay? Watch this. Grandmother: You can't catch me. You say it. You can't catch me. Children: You can't catch me. Grandmother: I'm the Gingerbread Man.Children: I'm the Gingerbread Man. Grandmother: Well done! Very good. SM: So what's happening here? I think what we need to look at is we need to look at learning as the product of educational self-organization. If you allow the educational process to self-organize, then learning emerges. It's not about making learning happen. It's about letting it happen. The teacher sets the process in motion and then she stands back in awe and watches as learning happens. I think that's what all this is pointing at. But how will we know? How will we come to know? Well, I intend to build these Self-Organized Learning Environments. They are basically broadband, collaboration and encouragement put together. I've tried this in many, many schools. It's been tried all over the world, and teachers sort of stand back and say, "It just happens by itself?" And I said, "Yeah, it happens by itself.""How did you know that?" I said, "You won't believe the children who told me and where they're from." Here's a SOLE in action. (Children talking) This one is in England. He maintains law and order, because remember, there's no teacher around. Girl: The total number of electrons is not equal to the total number of protons -- SM: Australia Girl: -- giving it a net positive or negative electrical charge. The net charge on an ion is equal to the number of protons in the ion minus the number of electrons. SM: A decade ahead of her time. So SOLEs, I think we need a curriculum of big questions. You already heard about that. You know what that means. There was a time when Stone Age men and women used to sit and look up at the sky and say, "What are those twinkling lights?" They built the first curriculum, but we've lost sight of those wondrous questions. We've brought it down to the tangent of an angle. But that's not sexy enough. The way you would put it to a nine-year-old is to say, "If a meteorite was coming to hit the Earth, how would you figure out if it was going to or not?" And if he says, "Well, what? how?" you say, "There's a magic word. It's called the tangent of an angle," and leave him alone. He'll figure it out. So here are a couple of images from SOLEs. I've tried incredible, incredible questions -- "When did the world begin? How will it end?" — to nine-year-olds. This one is about what happens to the air we breathe. This is done by children without the help of any teacher. The teacher only raises the question, and then stands back and admires the answer. So what's my wish? My wish is that we design the future of learning. We don't want to be spare parts for a great human computer, do we? So we need to design a future for learning. And I've got to -- hang on, I've got to get this wording exactly right, because, you know, it's very important. My wish is to help design a future of learning by supporting children all over the world to tap into their wonder and their ability to work together. Help me build this school. It will be called the School in the Cloud. It will be a school where children go on these intellectual adventures driven by the big questions which their mediators put in. The way I want to do this is to build a facility where I can study this. It's a facility which is practically unmanned. There's only one granny who manages health and safety. The rest of it's from the cloud. The lights are turned on and off by the cloud, etc., etc., everything's done from the cloud. But I want you for another purpose. You can do Self-Organized Learning Environments at home, in the school, outside of school, in clubs. It's very easy to do. There's a great document produced by TED which tells you how to do it. If you would please, please do it across all five continents and send me the data, then I'll put it all together, move it into the School of Clouds, and create the future of learning. That's my wish. And just one last thing. I'll take you to the top of the Himalayas. At 12,000 feet, where the air is thin, I once built two Hole in the Wall computers, and the children flocked there. And there was this little girl who was following me around. And I said to her, "You know, I want to give a computer to everybody, every child. I don't know, what should I do?" And I was trying to take a picture of her quietly. She suddenly raised her hand like this, and said to me, "Get on with it." (Laughter) (Applause) I think it was good advice. I'll follow her advice. I'll stop talking. Thank you. Thank you very much. (Applause) Thank you. Thank you. (Applause) Thank you very much. Wow. (Applause)
¿Cómo es posible? No saben nada". Mis colegas dijeron: "No, es una solución simple. Seguro que uno de tus estudiantes ha pasado por aquí y les enseñó cómo usar el ratón". Y yo: "Sí, es posible". Así que repetí el experimento. Me fui a casi 500 km de Delhi a un pueblo muy apartado donde las posibilidades de que pasara un ingeniero de software eran muy remotas. (Risas) Repetí allí el experimento. No había lugar para quedarse, así que coloqué mi computadora, me fui, volví un par de meses después, y encontré niños jugando con ella a videojuegos. Cuando me vieron, dijeron: "queremos un procesador más rápido y un ratón mejor". (Risas) Así que dije: "¿cómo narices saben todo esto?" Y me dijeron algo muy interesante. Con voz irritada, dijeron: "nos diste una máquina que sólo funciona en inglés, así que tuvimos que enseñarnos inglés para poder usarla". (Risas) Esa fue la primera vez, como profesor, que escuché la palabra "enseñarnos" dicha tan a la ligera. Aquí podemos echar un vistazo de esos años. Ese es el primer día en "Agujero en la pared" A su derecha hay un niño de ocho años. A su izquierda está su alumna. Ella tiene seis años. Y le está enseñando cómo navegar. Luego por otras partes del país, repetí esto una y otra vez, obteniendo exactamente los mismos resultados que teníamos. [Película: "Agujero en la pared", 1999] Una niña de ocho años diciéndole a su hermana mayor qué debe hacer. Y finalmente una niña explicando en la lengua maratí qué es y dice "hay un procesador dentro". Así que empecé a publicar. Publiqué en todas partes. Anoté y medí todo, y expliqué: en nueve meses, un grupo de niños a solas con una computadora en cualquier idioma llegarán al mismo nivel que una secretaria en Occidente. He visto que sucedía esto una y otra vez. Pero tenía curiosidad por saber, ¿qué otra cosa podrían hacer si podían hacer ya tanto? Empecé a experimentar con otras materias, entre ellas, por ejemplo, la pronunciación. Hay una comunidad de niños en el sur de India cuya pronunciación del inglés es muy mala y necesitaban una buena pronunciación, ya que mejoraría sus trabajos. Les instalé un convertidor de voz a texto en una computadora y les dije: "Sigan hablando hasta que la computadora escriba lo que Uds. dicen". (Risas) Y lo hicieron, vean un poco. Computadora: Gusto en conocerlo. Niño: Gusto en conocerlo. Sugata Mitra: La razón por la que terminé con la cara de esta joven de allí es porque sospecho que muchos de Uds. la conocen. Ella entró a un centro de llamadas en Hyderabad y puede que los haya torturado por sus tarjetas de crédito en un acento inglés muy claro. Así que la gente se preguntaba, ¿hasta dónde llegará? ¿Dónde se detendrá? Decidí que destruiría mi propio argumento al crear una proposición absurda. Planteé una hipótesis, una hipótesis ridícula. El tamil es una lengua autóctona del sur y dije: ¿pueden los niños de lengua tamil en una aldea del sur de India aprender la biotecnología de la replicación del ADN en inglés mediante una computadora puesta en la calle? Y pensé: los evaluaré. Obtendrán un cero. Lo dejaré un par de meses, lo voy a dejar un par de meses. Volveré, obtendrán otro cero. Volveré al laboratorio y diré que necesitamos profesores. Encontré un pueblo. Kallikuppam, al sur de India. Coloqué ahí computadoras en el "Agujero en la pared"; descargué todo tipo de cosas desde Internet sobre la replicación del ADN, la mayoría de los cuales yo no entendía. Los niños llegaron corriendo, dijeron: "¿qué es todo esto?" Así que les dije: "Es de gran actualidad, muy importante. Pero todo está en inglés". Ellos dijeron: "¿Cómo podemos entender esas palabras inglesas tan grandes y los diagramas y la química?" Para ese momento, había desarrollado un nuevo método pedagógico, así que lo apliqué. Les dije: "No tengo ni la más remota idea". (Risas) "Y, de todos modos, me voy". Los dejé un par de meses. Obtuvieron un cero. Les hice una prueba. Volví tras dos meses y los niños aparecieron y dijeron: "No hemos entendido nada". Así que me dije: "¿qué esperaba yo?" Les dije: "Está bien, pero ¿cuánto tiempo les llevó decidir que no habían entendido nada? Ellos dijeron: "No nos dimos por vencidos. Lo vemos todos los días". Así que le dije: "¿Cómo? No entienden estas pantallas y se quedan mirándolas durante dos meses? ¿Para qué?" Una niña que se ve en este momento, levantó la mano y me dijo en inglés y tamil deficiente: "Bueno, aparte del hecho de que la replicación indebida de la molécula de ADN provoca enfermedades, no hemos entendido nada más". (Risas) (Aplausos) Así que los puse a prueba. Tengo una imposibilidad educativa, de cero a 30 % en dos meses, bajo el calor tropical, con una computadora bajo el árbol en un idioma desconocido haciendo algo que se adelanta una década a su tiempo. Absurdo. Pero tenía que seguir la norma victoriana. El 30 % es un fracaso. ¿Cómo puedo hacer que aprueben? Tengo que conseguir 20 puntos más. No podía encontrar un profesor. Lo que sí encontré fue una amiga que tenía una hija de 22 años, contable, y que jugaba con ellos todo el tiempo. Así que le pregunté a la chica: "¿Puedes ayudarme?" Ella me dijo: "Claro que no. No tuve ciencias en la escuela. No tengo ni idea de lo que hacen bajo ese árbol durante todo el día. No te puedo ayudar". Le dije: "Te diré qué. Usa el método de la abuela". Ella me dice: "¿Qué es eso?" Le dije: "Ponte de pie detrás de ellos. Cada vez que hagan algo, solo di 'bueno, vaya, ¿cómo hicieron eso? ¿Cuál es la siguiente página? Cielos, a su edad yo nunca podría haber hecho eso'. Ya sabes lo que hacen las abuelas". Ella hizo eso dos meses más. Los resultados subieron a 50 %. Kallikuppam había alcanzado a mi escuela control de Nueva Delhi, una escuela privada rica con un profesor formado en biotecnología. Al ver ese gráfico sabía que hay una forma de nivelar el campo de juego. Aquí está Kallikuppam. (Niños hablando) Las neuronas... comunicación. Tengo el ángulo equivocado de la cámara. Es solo material de aficionado, pero lo que ella decía, como pudieron entender, era sobre las neuronas, con sus manos así, y decía que las neuronas se comunican. Con 12 años. Entonces, ¿cómo serán los trabajos? Bueno, ya sabemos cómo son hoy. ¿Cómo será el aprendizaje? Sabemos cómo es hoy, niños inmersos en sus teléfonos móviles por un lado yendo a regañadientes a la escuela llevando sus libros con la otra mano. ¿Cómo será mañana? ¿Será que ya no tendremos que ir a la escuela? ¿Podría ser que, en el momento en que necesiten saber algo, lo pueden averiguar en dos minutos? ¿Podría ser?... una pregunta devastadora, una pregunta que me planteó Nicholas Negroponte... ¿podría ser que nos estemos dirigiendo hacia o tal vez estemos en un futuro en el que el saber está obsoleto? Pero eso es terrible. Somos Homo sapiens. El saber es lo que nos distingue de los simios. Pero véanlo de esta manera. A la naturaleza le llevó 100 millones de años hacer que los simios se irguieran y se convirtieran en Homo sapiens. Nos costó sólo 10 000 años para que el saber se convirtiera en obsoleto. Qué logro es esto. Pero tenemos que integrar eso en nuestro propio futuro. El estímulo parece ser la clave. Si se fijan en Kuppam, si se fijan en todos los experimentos que hice, simplemente decía: "Guau", saludando al aprendizaje. Hay evidencia de la neurociencia. La parte reptil de nuestro cerebro localizada en el centro, cuando se siente amenazado, apaga todo lo demás, se apaga la corteza prefrontal, la parte del aprendizaje, apaga todo eso. Los castigos y los exámenes son vistos como amenazas. Tomamos a nuestros niños, les hacemos apagar sus cerebros y luego les decimos: "Funciona bien". ¿Por qué crearon un sistema así? Porque se necesitaba. Hubo una época en la Edad de los Imperios en que se necesitaba a aquellas personas que pudieran sobrevivir bajo amenaza. Cuando se está en una trinchera solo, si uno puede sobrevivir, está bien, aprobado. Si uno no lo logró, no aprobado. Pero la Edad de los Imperios se acabó. ¿Qué sucede con la creatividad en nuestra época? Tenemos que desplazar el equilibrio de la amenaza al placer. Volví a Inglaterra en busca de abuelas británicas. Puse avisos y documentos que decían: Si Ud. es una abuela británica, si tiene banda ancha y una cámara web, ¿me podría regalar una hora de su tiempo a la semana? Conseguí 200 en las primeras dos semanas. Conozco más abuelas británicas que nadie en el universo. (Risas) Se llaman la nube de abuelas. La nube de abuelas se sienta en Internet. Si hay un niño con problemas, lanzamos una abuela. Ella aparece en Skype y ordena las cosas. Las he visto hacerlo desde un pueblo llamado Diggles en el noroeste de Inglaterra, al interior de un aldea en Tamil Nadu, India, a casi 10 000 km. Lo hace con un solo gesto antiquísimo. "Shhh". ¿De acuerdo? Vean esto. Abuela: No me puedes atrapar. Díganlo Uds. No me puedes atrapar. Niños: No me puedes atrapar. Abuela: Soy el hombre de jengibre. Niños: Soy el hombre de jengibre. Abuela: ¡Bien hecho! Muy bien. SM: ¿Qué está pasando aquí? Creo que lo que tenemos que mirar es al aprendizaje como el producto de la autoorganización educacional. Si se permite que el proceso educativo se autoorganice, entonces surge el aprendizaje. No se trata de hacer que el aprendizaje ocurra. Se trata de dejar que suceda. El profesor pone en marcha el proceso y luego se pone de pie de nuevo con asombro y observa como el aprendizaje ocurre. Creo que a eso apunta todo esto. Pero, ¿cómo lo sabremos? ¿Cómo vamos a llegar a saberlo? Bueno, intento construir estos Entornos de Aprendizaje Auto-Organizados. [EAAO] Son, básicamente, Internet de banda ancha, colaboración y estímulo colocados juntos. Lo he intentado en muchas escuelas, muchos años. Ha sido probado en todo el mundo y los profesores dan una suerte de paso atrás y dicen: "¿Surge por sí mismo?" Y yo: "Sí, surge por sí mismo". Y ellos: "¿Cómo lo sabes?" Y yo: "No creerás qué niños me lo dijeron y de dónde son". Aquí hay un EAAO en acción. (Niños hablando) Este está en Inglaterra. Él mantiene la ley y el orden porque, recuerden, no hay un profesor cerca. Chica: El total de electrones no es igual a la cantidad total de protones - SM: Australia Chica: dándole un neto positivo de carga eléctrica negativa. La carga neta de un ión es igual a la cantidad de protones en el ión menos el número de electrones. SM: Una década por delante de su tiempo. Son EAAOs, creo que necesitamos un plan de estudios de grandes preguntas. Ya han oído hablar de eso. Saben lo que eso significa. Hubo un tiempo en el que los hombres y mujeres de la Edad de Piedra solían sentarse, mirar al cielo y decir: "¿Qué son esas luces parpadeantes?" Construyeron el primer plan de estudios, pero hemos olvidado estas preguntas maravillosas. Lo hemos reducido a la tangente de un ángulo. Pero eso no es lo suficientemente atractivo. La forma de decírselo a un niño de nueve años es: "Si un meteorito fuera a chocar con la Tierra, ¿cómo saber si chocará o no?" Y si él dice: "Bueno, ¿qué?, ¿cómo?" Uds. dicen: "Hay una palabra mágica. Se llama la tangente de un ángulo" y lo dejan en paz. Él va a averiguarlo. Así que aquí hay un par de imágenes de los EAAOs. He probado preguntas increíbles. "¿Cuándo comenzó el mundo? ¿Cómo terminará?", a niños de nueve años. Esta es sobre qué sucede con el aire que respiramos. Esto lo han hecho los niños sin la ayuda de ningún profesor. El maestro solo plantea la cuestión y luego retrocede y admira la respuesta. ¿Cuál es mi deseo? Mi deseo es que diseñemos el futuro del aprendizaje. No queremos ser repuestos de una gran computadora humana excelente, ¿verdad? Así que tenemos que diseñar un futuro para el aprendizaje. Y tengo que... esperen, tengo que decir esto correctamente, porque, ya saben, es muy importante. Mi deseo es ayudar a diseñar un futuro de aprendizaje mediante el apoyo a los niños de todo el mundo aprovechando su asombro y su capacidad de trabajar juntos. Ayúdenme a construir esta escuela. Se va a llamar la escuela en la nube. Va a ser una escuela donde los niños se adentrarán a aventuras intelectuales impulsados por las grandes preguntas planteadas por sus mediadores. La forma en que quiero hacerlo es construir una instalación donde pueda estudiar esto. Es una instalación que prácticamente no tiene personas. Solo hay una abuelita que gestiona la salud y la seguridad. El resto es de la nube. La nube enciende y apaga las luces, etc., etc., todo se hace desde la nube. Pero los quiero para otro propósito. Pueden hacer Entornos de Aprendizaje Auto-Organizado en casa, en la escuela, fuera de la escuela, en clubes. Es muy fácil de hacer. Hay un gran documento producido por TED que les dice cómo hacerlo. Si lo desean, por favor, por favor háganlo en los cinco continentes y me envían los datos, entonces lo pondré todo junto, y lo colocaré en la escuela en la nube, y crear el futuro del aprendizaje. Ese es mi deseo. Y una última cosa. Los llevaré a la cima del Himalaya. A 3600 m , donde hay poco aire, donde una vez empotré dos computadoras en el agujero en la pared y los niños acudían allí. Y había una niña que me seguía. Y yo le dije: "Sabes, quiero darle una computadora a todos, a todos los niños. No sé, ¿qué debería hacer?" Y yo estaba tratando de tomar una foto de ella discretamente. De pronto levantó la mano, así, y me dijo: "Hazlo". (Risas) (Aplausos) Creo que fue un buen consejo. Seguiré su consejo. Dejaré de hablar. Gracias. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos) Gracias. Gracias. (Aplausos) Muchas gracias. ¡Guau! (Aplausos)